Sherlock Holmes The rediscovered Railway
Mysteries and Other Stories by John
Taylor read by Benedict Cumberbatch
[Music]
an inscrutable masquerade
in a draw in the Bureau of an upstairs
room of my current home there is a
locked cedar wood box which I inherited
as a youth from my grandfather
this is one might say my box of Secrets
when I was young it contained the
treasures of Boyhood a catapult a lump
of beeswax the carapace of a crab
for many years since it has been the
repository of an archive admittedly a
ragged and disordered archive a
collection of notes and scribblings
concerning some of the many cases of my
lifelong friend the Consulting detective
Sherlock Holmes which for one reason or
another I never took the travel to write
into proper reports
having had recently a little time on my
hands I reopened this box of yellowing
notebooks and it seemed to me that
several of the cases given the ocean of
time between those events and the
present day would now bear telling
and I begin by chronicling an adventure
which I may have dismissed for several
reasons not because it lacked baffling
and intriguing elements on the contrary
but mostly I think because it was for me
personally such a dizzying and
distressing experience
it was a Wednesday evening in July at
the end of a day of Street jacketing
Heat
and I sat next to the open window of our
parlor at Baker Street drinking in the
air and hoping for the liberating Ripple
of a breeze
the newspaper on my lap reported the
release from police custody of a known
criminal Tobias organ arrested some days
previously for the murder of Max
Zimmerman a money lender shot through
the head in his small apartment in
Wardle Street
in the end they'd been insufficient
evidence to charge organ with murder
even though the police clearly thought
him culpable
strangely enough I had once met organ
myself he had come to me as a patient
suffering as I recall from a severe
lesion to the lower back which he
maintained had been caused by a fall
against a metal stanchion but which I
had little doubt was in fact a stab
wound my diagnosis was supported I
Believe by his barely Veiled Threat that
I should under no circumstances make
known his injury to anyone else
he had an unforgettable menacing way
with him and I had felt immense relief
when he left my surgery
I'd been looking forward to discussing
the organ case with Holmes who would
certainly have some views on the subject
but when he finally appeared for dinner
he was irritable and uncommunicative and
from these symptoms I guessed him to be
in the process of some taxing mental
work
all the same I had no wish to sit out
the meal in silence
stifling weather to be out and about
homes I said peppering a slice of beef
indeed Watson and equally stifling to be
in
he visited himself with cutting into a
potato
after a while I said I've not seen you
today I presume you were somewhere on
business
yes Watson I was
another pause the of cutlery
somewhere local somewhere very local
Watson I'd expect you'd like to know
where well I I have no wish to be
intrusive in the basement I've been all
day in the basement of our house and
since your desire not to be intrusive is
clearly struggling against your
overwhelming curiosity to know I will
tell you why I was there
and he paused and smiled in the full
confidence that you will not breathe a
word to a soul about it
my homes of course not and on the
understanding that if I do tell you you
will not be able to leave this house
until my work is complete what
I put down almost dropped my knife and
fork we don't mean not leave at all
that's precisely what I mean so it may
be that you would prefer to forego my
secret rather than consent to becoming a
prisoner here for what might be several
days
hopelessly intrigued I gave no thought
to the discomfort of being shut indoors
in this sultry heat no thought to the
boredom not even any thought to the fact
that I had appointments in my diary
I'm prepared to abide by your request
homes
he stood up from the table his meal
unfinished and went across to the Hearth
to retrieve his pipe and tobacco pouch
as he filled his pipe and lit it he sank
into his armchair
I believe you have been preoccupied with
the case of Tobias organ Watson
yes it has been on my mind how you twice
left the newspaper open at that page
the money lender Zimmerman a legitimate
businessman with a wife and young
children was murdered with an army rifle
the police have many reasons for
believing Tobias organ to be guilty of
the crime of one of these is that he
owns an army rifle
organ of course denies that his firearm
is the murder weapon well yes I said one
would expect he would but suppose said
Holmes Suppose there was a science which
could with certainty tie a bullet to the
gun which fired it now that would be
marvelous I said but that isn't is there
well Watson let us say that such a
science is seminal it is exactly this
problem which I am wrestling with at
present in the basement of the house
I've set up a laboratory of sorts down
there where I can conduct some
experiments progress is promising and if
the results are as I expect they will
certainly send Tobias organ to The
Gallows but organ is an utterly ruthless
villain undoubtedly guilty of a number
of murders but devious enough always to
Palm them off on others if he were to
gain even an inkling of my work we would
be in the utmost Danger
but I can see that you would be in
danger homes but how might I be as I say
Watson organ is ruthless to get at any
enemy his favorite trick is to abduct
someone close to his adversary often
with I'm afraid horrific consequences
you know too much now and since I'm not
prepared to put you at risk in that way
I fear you must sit it out in these
apartments you must not answer the door
you must stay away from the windows no
visitors you must lead the life of a
prisoner until such time as this matter
is settled
well I said it might be good for me I
have a medical paper to write in the
period of confinement might induce me to
keep my nose to my studies
excellent Watson I'm sure your sacrifice
will not be in vain
I really did not see myself sacrificing
very much at all
I spent the evening canceling all
appointments of the following week and
went to bed rather looking forward to a
few days of fruitful incarceration
the morning found me in a hopeful mood
in what appeared to be an empty house
Holmes I presumed had already descended
to his basement laboratory our landlady
Mrs Hudson had left me a pleasant cold
breakfast an indication that she herself
had had to leave the house early the day
while already warm and bright had not
yet begun to turn oppressive the clock
over the half ticked slowly as I settled
down to my books experiencing for the
first time since my student years some
of the quiet Ecstasy of study
by midday the room had become hot
my concentration meandered and thirst
plagued me
I wandered downstairs to Mrs Hudson's
apartment and found her still absent so
I proceeded down to the basement to ask
Holmes whether he knew what arrangements
had been made for lunch the door to the
basement was shut and when I tried the
handle I found it to be locked from
within I could hear the occasional crack
of what sounded like a gun being fired
and the grind of metal on metal like
ball bearings rolling round and Iron
Bowl
homes are you there
Watson what are you doing here
I'm in the process of an investigation
indeed yes I'm trying to find out what's
happening about luncheon we'll have to
prepare something for yourself he called
back I'm afraid I've sent Mrs Hudson
away I cannot risk the lives of innocent
people and Watson be so good as to keep
away from the basement
confine yourself to our own rooms and to
the kitchen there's a good fellow very
well Holmes but yes
I really would very much like a
newspaper
I'm afraid you must too without neither
of us could take the chance of leaving
here until this business is complete now
please let me get on
I trundled to the kitchen I managed to
find myself some bread and cheese which
I took back upstairs
our rooms were now very hot and since I
was forbidden to sit near the window I
ate my luncheon over my books dropping
crumbs into the creases of Gray's
Anatomy and beginning to feel Restless
after lunch I managed to force myself to
a little more work but by three o'clock
had fallen asleep in the armchair
I woke to hear the sounds of evening
traffic moving along Baker Street
I listened with something like Envy to
the busy hubbub of those who were free
to come and go who had families to
return to and simple feasts awaiting
them at convivial tables
my lot seemed Bleak by comparison Holmes
did not emerge from his infernal
basement and Mrs Hudson did not appear
with an evening meal
I cannot recall how the rest of the
evening passed the heat absorbed during
the day by London's Pavements now
radiated back to thicken the evening air
the world outside of which I had no news
became gradually silent and I hungry and
disconsolate went finally to bed
the next morning after a makeshift
breakfast I got down to some work and
was well into the argument of the paper
I was writing when I began to realize
that the room was again beginning to
become airless and oven-like
determined not to succumb to lethargy as
I had the previous afternoon I decided
that despite whom's strict embargo on
going near the window I simply must have
some air
as I raised the sash I saw a cab
approaching along Baker Street and
stopping directly beneath the window
the passenger who stepped out was
Nicholas Cartwright an old University
friend now writing for the times
I hadn't seen him for a couple of months
and he seemed about to pay a surprise
visit
desperate as I was for company I could
not forget the promise I had made to
Holmes to admit no visitors the doorbell
rang
my first idea was to wait for Cartwright
to give up and go away but there quickly
came a second ring and with it a call
from the street through the now open
window Martin
a note of anxiety in his voice
suggesting that all was not well
Cartwright was a good friend
I did not see how I could linger there
pretending to be deaf when he might be
in need of my help
I dashed down the stairs and opened the
front door
Watson so pleased to have found you
the statement immediately struck me as
odd as did Cartwright's whole demeanor
but mindful of the proximity of homes in
his makeshift laboratory I whispered
local chap odd things are going on come
up as quietly as you can I'll explain
there a sudden sharp crack issued from
the depths of the house and I hoped that
preoccupied as he was Holmes would have
no inkling of the presence of my visitor
as we entered the Parlor and shut the
door Cartwright said
Watson I've been worried about you
I didn't even know if I'd find you here
worried yes the story in The Gazette
regarding yourself and Mr Holmes did you
know it was in the papers
Cartwright I haven't the least idea what
you're talking about and as for
newspapers I haven't seen one in days
here he tossed me the paper open at
about the third or fourth page and I
read the following headline in
accompanying article
Sherlock Holmes and Dr Watson part
company
after several years of celebrated
collaboration the eminent Consulting
detective Mr Sherlock Holmes in his
medical companion Dr John Watson
have terminated their professional
partnership and it seems simultaneously
ended their personal friendship
Mr Holmes said that Wally continued to
hold Dr Watson in high esteem and to
regard him as a matter of exceptional
honor and professional competence
circumstances upon which he could not
and would not elaborate had made it
expedient for them to go their separate
ways
there was no comment from Dr Watson
I stood for a moment holding the
newspaper and diverting my gaze from
Cartwright
who had written this did Holmes know
about it
was there some truth in it was Holmes is
exiled to the basement a way of keeping
me at Bay while he found alternative
lodgings
this is today's Gazette yes Watson I see
you knew nothing about this
am I speaking to you as a friend
Cartwright or as a journalist well I
suppose unfortunately as a friend John I
say unfortunately because this is
clearly a damn good story but if you
wish to talk to me off the Record so be
it
off the Record then
I know nothing of this and I don't know
whether Holmes has had a hand in it he's
conducting some very secret business at
present and possibly it's connected to
that that's all I can tell you I'm
afraid
one thing does baffle me Cartwright said
how did The Gazette get the story
without us getting it too anyway I won't
make anything of this John until you
give me the go-ahead but I hope if there
does turn out to be an exclusive
you'll be the one to get it I said Thank
You Nicholas I saw him down the stairs
and closed the front door behind him
finding myself relieved that he had gone
I had no idea that I would be singing
him again soon under even more peculiar
circumstances
but determined that now I must confront
homes with this business
I knocked on the door of the basement
homes
a long silence
ohms we must speak
not now Watson
Holmes there's something I must discuss
with you urgently something in the
newspaper
there was a scuffling in the basement
door opened
newspaper how did you get a newspaper
Cartwright called he'd seen an article
yes Holmes interrupted yes the article
I dare say you would appreciate an
explanation
give me half an hour
a little later we sat opposite one
another in our sitting room the evening
was still close and oppressive
the newspaper article said Holmes was an
unfortunate necessity
I hope it has not caused you too much
embarrassment Watson and when this
business is finished all will be
rectified
why I said reporters is having quarreled
bear with me Watson I beg of you
as you know I have tried to keep my work
here secret but how certain can one be
of that the police are involved in these
matters and are aware of my experiments
and who knows whether some junior or
even senior member of the force is not
in League with that utterly ruthless
villain
now
having been alerted to that newspaper
report might it not be the case that
Tobias organ would assume that you were
no longer in London at any rate he would
certainly be likely to assume you were
no longer sharing these premises with me
you gave the story to The Gazette to
protect me yes Watson that was my
purpose
I just wish that you'd consulted me
first
you were not supposed even to know about
it Watson and if you had not had a visit
from Cartwright you would never have
seen the article it was unfortunate that
he came when he did
it was the article that brought him yes
a miscalculation on my part
now it is late work to do tomorrow and I
must insist on extracting from you
another guarantee what's that Holmes
that you will not under any
circumstances interrupt my work again
it's all very delicate in a disturbance
at an inopportune moment could ruin
everything is that clear not under any
circumstance
that night I lay awake in the muggy heat
the bed clothes pulled back and grieved
for what I calculated to be the death of
my reputation
at least I imagined that's how the world
would see it or at least that portion of
the world that reads the London Gazette
Holmes and Watson have parted company
but there is no comment from Watson only
a nobly worded valediction from the
Greek Detective
such bitter thoughts polluted my
Restless waking and tormented my
subsequent dreams
and added to all this their layers
sensed that things were still not clear
that something crucial remained unspoken
I woke early but exhausted without going
near the window I took in what I could
of the Awakening day
the street was quiet
I dressed slowly and descended to the
kitchen to find something to eat the
rattles and sharp cracks of homes's
experiments had already come to life
below in the basement
and they wondered whether he had even
bothered to go to bed
I was making a pot of tea when the
doorbell sounded
the noises from The Cellar did not pause
so I assumed that Holmes had not heard
the Bell
I could see nothing off the front of the
house from the kitchen but after I'd
taken a few steps up into the lobby it
became clear by means of a side window
that the visitor was once again Nicholas
Cartwright
I went to the door and admitted him
cut right
what's going on Watson
what do you mean I mean what game is
being played here
cut right I've no idea what you're
referring to you better come up
he was I could tell steaming with anger
though I had no idea what I could have
done to arouse it he would not sit he
stood with his arms behind his back a
man preparing to deliver an accusation
you told me you were inescapably
confined to this house
yes Cartwright and so I have been this
is the third day excluding yesterday
night you mean no I was here yesterday
night too tossing and turning in my bed
at them thought of my ruined reputation
see here yesterday you prevailed upon my
friendship by confiding in me matters
which as a journalist I considered more
than worthy of publication
had I known that you were deceiving me
Cartwright you have my word I was not
deceiving you I have not left this house
since Monday afternoon
so you have a twin brother no I do not
then please explain to me who was the
man outside the restaurant at marlabone
station at five past midnight
I take it he resembled me more than
resembled I do hope you're being
truthful with me Watson
I could see that his suspicions were not
a laid I even began to wonder whether my
Restless period of waking the previous
night had itself been a dream and
whether I had been sleepwalking
such things are possible I know and the
heat my fatigue and the events of the
last days had left me so baffled that in
that moment of confusion I could not
entirely rule it out
what happened he said was that I was
walking through the station Concourse
when I spotted you by the wall of the
restaurant which by then was closed
talking to a man in a brown felt hat I
would have approached you but when I
caught your eye you cut me as dead as if
you didn't know me and I assumed your
conversation was of some importance
the more I thought about it the more I
thought it was a poor way to treat a
good friend
suddenly the fog in my brain gave way to
an horrific clarity
I knew that I must rid myself of
Cartwright at once
thank you for telling me this I said it
is of the utmost importance but Nicholas
and I pray you won't take this amiss
I must ask you to leave
to leave please this is a fearfully
serious business
there is real Danger
you're not just trying to get me out of
the way Watson that's exactly what I'm
trying to do Cartwright but preferred a
very good reason believe me you will
have your story
very well John very well
at the front door he patted me amiably
on the shoulder
I shut the door on him and leaned
against the wall trying to get my
thoughts in order
Holmes had instructed me not under any
circumstances to trouble him again
yet this situation was possibly critical
if Tobias organ had hired some
impersonated look and sound so like me
that even Cartwright who had known me
for years could be convinced then Holmes
might also be deceived and then
what power they would have in their
hands
if I could not speak to Holmes I could
at least alert him by other means
I ran up the stairs with the idea of
writing a note which I could slip under
the basement door but as I reached our
rooms I heard a cry from the street
without thinking I ran to the Parlor
window a hundred yards southwards along
Baker Street three men were struggling
two of them were bundling the third man
into a cab against his will
it was Cartwright
I dashed down the stairs and ran into
the street the driver of the cab had
already whipped up the horse and moved
off at a lick but I gave Chase Fury and
outrage fuming my progress I pursued
them for a good half a mile until
eventually they are paced me and I stood
gasping for breath outside Saint
Vincent's church
sat on the pavement
I needed Holmes's help
the transgression of a broken promise
was a trivial thing surely in the
context of this appalling incident
I would go to him immediately
aware that in the haste of my Pursuit
I'd left the front door of the house
open
a new anxiety overcame me
clearly this kidnap was the work of
organs Ruffians and who was to say that
they would not take advantage of an open
door I trotted as priskly as I could
back to Baker Street
but the door was no longer open
and on such a close and windless day I
thought it unlikely it had been closed
by a draft
the horrible thought occurred to me that
someone may have already got in
and then everything seemed to Tumble
into place Cartwright's abduction had
been intended to draw me out of the
house so that the man masquerading as
myself could gain entry
Holmes would be unaware of this he would
eventually open the door of the basement
to his assailant and believing it was
myself he was admitting would offer the
easiest of targets I'd left the house
without a key but I knew there was a
possibility of access via the rear of
the Terrace
this entailed my knocking at the door of
our neighbor Mrs Harbin an elderly
amiable woman who seemed happy to allow
me access to the rear of the building
here I was obliged to scale a wall to
the yard outside the back of our own
dingy basement the front room being that
which Holmes had taken for his makeshift
Laboratory
there was no Light Within
I opened the door with infinite slowness
the noise of Holmes's experiments seemed
to have stopped
the door that connected this room to the
front half of the basement was six or
seven short Paces away but it was too
dark to see whether the bare floorboards
were liable to move and groan when I
trod upon them
I tested each step before lowering my
weight and moved with the floating
motion of a rather overweight pantomime
artist one
two three then there was movement behind
me a hand was clamped across my mouth
and an arm locked around my throat the
grip was expert I could not breathe or
move the hot breath of my assailant in
my ear whispered oh God
do not cry out
I'm gonna release you a new turn around
slowly and face me you must
you must cap our hand if you understand
I reached up to the hand around my
throat and obediently I tapped it the
arm released me and as quietly as I
could I took a deep draft of air turning
as I did so astrayed shhh yes doctor
wasn't expecting you here or rather in a
sense I was but since you are just about
to arrive I wasn't expecting you to come
in the back way as well the policeman
smirked at his little conundrum when he
explained to me I began what on Earth
you mean not now doctor he said
glad you're here though sir an
additional pair of ears up close to the
door now and listen it won't be long
it was indeed less than a minute before
we heard the door from the front of the
house opening into the laboratory and
the arrival of what sounded like two men
the door was closed with a thump and a
Gruff voice said
so this is it yes this is where he's
working
there was something familiar about that
second voice and he won't be back for a
while no but half an hour I should think
at that moment with a shock I recognized
the other voice it was my own
I tend to lestrade again but he just put
his finger to his lips and indicated
that I should continue to listen
so what's the plan then ask the graph
Voice Within to match the bullet that
killed maximum with the ones from your
gun said my voice
the police know you killed him but they
need homes to provide them with evidence
that will convince a jury
evidently I thought the gruff character
is Tobias organ I heard him Pace about
then spit noisily
Zimmerman's not the first one I've
topped and they've never got me yet they
say you only got four pounds 10
Shillings from him never you mind what I
got
anyway I never killed him just for the
money I killed him because he gave me a
bad look he gave me a bad look and I
gave him a bad headache a bullet right
between the eyes
now let's deal with this little problem
suddenly there was a tumultuous crash as
if one of the walls had fallen in here
we go doctor said lestrade he pushed the
door harder we rushed into the
laboratory where organ had kicked
Holmes's equipment flying in all
directions and where to my amazement I
saw that he was now being attacked by
myself a perfect duplicate of me cracked
him a right hook then a left hook and
then filled him with a blow to the side
of the head organ hit the floor like a
sack of cabbages lestrade was on him in
a Flash cuffing organ's arms behind his
back lestrade blew his whistle and then
proceeded to arrest him
as I stood back to get a better look at
my other self the duplicate doctor put a
hand to his own face wrenched at his
upper brow and pulled and stretched
until he had removed his entire face
revealing beneath the peeling mask the
flaming eyes of Sherlock Holmes
the next moment lestrade's officers came
bursting through the basement door and
Tobias organ was dragged away
the heat of the day had given way at
last to a pleasant evening
Mrs Hudson had returned to the house and
provided homes and myself with an
excellent evening meal
now we sat with our brandies and homes
with his pipe at the open window where a
gentle breeze lifted the curtains and
refreshed The Parlor
as you will have deduced Holmes was
saying by way of explaining it all to me
the object of the Masquerade was to lure
organ somewhere where we could extract a
confession from him by subterfuge but
your ballistics experiments I said would
they not have been enough to convict him
it is a science only in the imagination
Holmes said
and though one day I'm certain it will
be more than that that is much more work
to do than I could accomplish in a
fortnight but lestrade and I agree that
if organ believed himself to be at risk
from my experiments he would wish to
destroy them what on Earth were you
doing in their homes if the thing was a
complete hoax
I'm afraid I did deceive you a little I
was not in there all the time the
mechanism of an Old Railway clock and a
device employing elastic and a drum skin
were intended to give the ear the
impression of ongoing industry well it
certainly deceived me I said but was it
really necessary for me to be
incarcerated for the duration
I'm afraid so my friend if organ through
one of his spies had got wind that there
were two Watsons the trick would not
have worked
what's more it was necessary for him to
believe that you and I had quarreled and
therefore that the good Dr Watson might
be in the market for a bit of betrayal
unfortunately your friend Cartwright saw
me meeting organs accomplice at malaban
station and almost let the cat out of
the bag it was necessary for us to put
him somewhere safe lestrade's men kindly
subjected him to a temporary and very
comfortable period of kidnap it was you
who had dragged away
yes I had not calculated that you would
follow him of course or that you would
be locked out and find yourself
clamoring in through the back
but it turned out well you will make an
additional witness for the prosecution
do you think they'll convict him oh yes
Watson his confession today was as clear
as a bell Tobias organ will hang
as for you my friend I have given you a
terrible time and as a reward I'm going
to take you to the Opera tonight yes
tonight Gilbert and Sullivan the Mercado
but Holmes my memory is you don't much
like Gilbert and Sullivan no Watson but
you do and besides
I have to confess to having a soft spot
for the Lord High executioner
[Music]
the conundrum of coach 13.
on an October morning when rain streamed
from the black clouds that swept above
our Baker Street lodgings
I found my friend Sherlock Holmes in a
similarly overcast mood
he had not had a case in weeks not at
least what he called a decent case and
he had been huffing and puffing about
the house for two days
it was with some relief to both of us
therefore that we heard the slowing
approach of a cab in the street outside
and both moved eagerly to the window the
handsome did indeed stop directly beside
our door and after a moment a large and
finely dressed middle-aged gentleman
emerged into the downpour paid his fare
and rang our doorbell Holmes was smiling
now what could make a rich American so
distressed Watson that he would come
pelmel here to us from Paddington
an American I said drawn irresistibly as
usual into Holmes's tantalizing games
certainly and I think a formidable
character
and you wish to tell me how you deduce
all that homes
I deduce his distress and his
nationality from the fact that he just
tried to pay the cabbie in American
dollars before recalling which pocket
held his Pounds Sterling as for his
coming from Paddington that was the
easiest of all for the driver of the
handsome is Henry Brown I'm surprised
you do not recognize him who always
works from the Paddington rank as ever
Watson I apologize for the banality of
these observations but you did ask
by now there were footsteps on the
stairs as Mrs Hudson escorted the
visitor to our apartment
while I inwardly delighted to note that
my friend had returned to his amiable
best in anticipation of a new challenge
I find myself praying that it would be a
challenge worthy of his powers and his
pent-up Energies
no sooner had the door opened than the
huge returned figure of our visitor
bright in a cream suit burst into the
room like an actor onto a stage
determined to establish his character
instantly Mr Holmes boomed the American
voices both his arms swept forward to
grasp my right hand Benedict Masterson
what a great privilege to meet you
delighted but I am Dr John Watson I
replied this is Mr Sherlock Holmes with
equally booming apologies he bowed
charmingly to me and turned to my friend
ah yes now I see
unmistakable unmistakable
the impression given was that he had
found the first Sherlock Holmes of his
acquaintance a little short of his
expectations
Mr Holmes I wish to ask you to act for
me in a business both mysterious and
distressing
you had better sit down Mr Masterson
said Holmes and tell us everything
and having settled his cream-covered
bulk into an armchair and accepted a
cigar on which he continued to Puff
anxiously as he spoke the American told
us his story
I am a dealer in Gold gentlemen gold has
been my life
my father owned small minds in Nevada
which gave us a comfortable living in my
turn through judicious trading I've made
these assets yield a fortune I came to
London last week because your own Bank
of England had made an order for a
substantial quantity of gold bars to
boost its Reserves
the bullion was shipped into Bristol
Harbor and transferred yesterday onto a
chartered London train for transfer to
the bank
I have been in London doing the
paperwork of which there is let me
assure you no small amount
and I went to Paddington this morning to
meet the consignment the train was there
the gold was not
I see said Holmes
stolen
undoubtedly how much we're talking four
or five Millions Mr Holmes that's a
large loss is the gold insured indeed it
is but you know insurance companies Mr
Holmes they are ever suspicious and the
circumstances of the Gold's
disappearance are to say the least
rather strange the details Mr Masterson
said my friend if you please
well continued Masterson tapping a thick
cylinder of Ash into the ashtray I had
asked a commission a special an
overnight train and also insisted that
it be discreet not armored or escorted
or in any way having the appearance of a
specially secured conveyance
I was offered the charter of a passenger
train which returns empty from Bristol
to London once a week and which real
women jokingly call the bad luck special
not because anything has ever happened
to it but because it normally consists
of 13 empty passenger coaches as indeed
it did on this occasion
I insisted that the gold be packed in
steel containers each locked with a
unique key
you will appreciate the goal itself
gentlemen is a weighty medal so each box
contained only as many bars as would
enable the containers to be carried in
order to prevent the possibility of them
being removed from the moving train I
ensured that while it was small enough
to go through the open Carriage door
they were too large to pass through the
windows even with the window slid down
to their largest aperture
I then arranged for the doors of the
bullion Carriage to be locked from the
outside so they could not be open until
the train reached London the train was
empty then apart from the driver and
farming of the locomotive
no Mr Holmes it is Railway practice for
all trains to have a guard a practice I
was very happy to comply with since it
meant my Consignment would have an
overseer throughout its journey and to
this end all the steel cases were loaded
into the last coach of the train coach
13 where the guard could keep a constant
watch on them the man employed for the
job was a Mr Lions Mr John Lyons a
mature and trusted employee of the
Railway company
here strangely Mr Masterson stopped and
smiled I uh I inquired whether he had
ever worked on the French Railways guard
Lions DC
guard de Leon
Holmes smiled politely and nodded
well forgive me gentlemen I could never
resist upon to continue the train left
Bristol at three this morning as
scheduled but when it arrived at
Paddington at six the steel boxes of
gold were gone
Mr Holmes this was an impossible robbery
the train stopped only once for a minute
or so to take on water hardly time to
unload a single box of bullying let
alone a hundred of the darn things
weighing in at 150 pounds apiece
and the god asked Holmes Lions claimed
that he fell asleep somewhere near the
journey awoke to find the bullying
disappeared he's being held a Paddington
along with the driver and engineer but
all ardently protest their innocence and
with regard to other suspects can you
think of anyone in your organization who
might feel inclined to take advantage of
you Masterson pinched his lips and
looked embarrassed
well if I may confide something to you
in the strictest confidence my estranged
wife Laura still has shares in the
company she believes that she should
have more there is uh
some bitterness in this regard however I
know Laura well enough to doubt that she
is a thief my friend simply said Thank
you Mr Masterson I will certainly take
the case on
would you be so good as to why Bristol
and inform them that Dr Watson and I are
on our way I will sir you mean to go
there today
indeed yes as soon as I have made a
check or two at Paddington Station
well I surely thank you I can think of
no better hands in which to leave the
case of the bad luck special than those
of Mr sheer luck Holmes
Holmes did not smile
I never leave anything to chance Mr
Masterson
perspicacity and reason are the tools I
employ forgive me Mr Holmes as I say I
am fairly attracted to puns
we will keep you in touch Holmes said
with all developments
within half an hour we were at
Paddington but before boarding the
Bristol train Holmes wish to make
certain that the so-called bad luck
special was Secure
the train had been shunted into a siding
and we were relieved to find the police
responsibility for the case had fallen
to inspect a Stanley Hopkins a young but
ambitious detective with whom Holmes and
myself had had numerous dealings in the
past
hearing that we were being engaged by Mr
Benedict Masterson the inspector agreed
to watch over the train and make sure it
remained undisturbed until our return to
London
it was still raining when we arrived at
Bristol where we met the station Foreman
George Willits an amiable man in his 50s
who gave the comforting impression of
having been in his job for a lifetime
and knowing the whole business inside
out
Willits had been on duty the previous
night and took us directly to the goods
platform from which the bullion train
had left
though he did his best to be of
assistance he looked painfully weary
I apologize you gents for my appearance
he said
but I was on night shift last night
seeing out the special
was just about to go off when the
message came from London about the theft
so I've not yet been on the bed we won't
keep you long will it Holmes said I
understand you were here when the
bullion boxes were being loaded I was
here he supervised them myself watched
them being lifted in the guards Carriage
at this very spot before I sent the
signal to bring in the rest of the Train
the guards coach was not connected to
the train while it was loaded that's
right sir the rest of the train was
shutted out of the siding and then
coupled up just before she would leave
and who brought her in Tommy Mariette
the engineer in his farm and Pat
mcglinchey old hands not quite so much a
fixture as myself Mr romes but they've
been around the best part of 10 years
they're sound men
good
now if you'll bear with me a little
longer will it I'd like to ask you a
little more about the gold itself how
many men were involved in loading the
carriage
well sir it was quite some operation
took four men to load each box two
inside the carriage two outside damn
heavy things if you'll excuse me sir
over a hundred weight a piece and damn
awkward squeezing him through them
narrow doors it was out of a job and how
long would you say the whole business
took it was about half past midnight
when they started in about a quarter
before two by the time they finished so
almost 80 minutes and after it was
loaded was there any delay before
departure no sir the rest of the train
as I say was reversed in from the soil
John Lyons the guard got aboard and the
door of the guards coach was locked from
without sir as per our instructions one
final question will it's if I may I'm
informed the train stopped on Route yes
sir she was scheduled to hold up for a
minute or so at Swindon to take on water
it stopped for no longer than that and
at no other time no sir the signalman
would know for sure she'd been held over
for more than a minute and that's
already been checked
Holmes seemed to pause for a moment
while he considered all this information
and then he said
well it's I'm most grateful for your
detailed and I have no doubt accurate
Recollections now if you will excuse us
Dr Watson and I will take the next train
back to London and leave you to go home
and get some sleep
inspector Hopkins was at Paddington when
we arrived and Holmes immediately
requested that he arranged for us to
speak to the railway man who had
commandeered the bad luck special on the
previous night Marriott and mcglinchey
the engineer and farman and the guard
lions
in a dark Office of the Railway men's
Quarters on one of the Grimmer outer
platforms of Paddington Station the
three men sat disconsolately on rickety
wooden chairs it occurred to me that
they had by now been detained in this
dismal place for several hours
and when Holmes and I were introduced to
Lions he barely had the energy to nod to
us but he did speak
his words almost drowned in the muffler
which half covered his mouth
I dare say you think me a thief Mr Rose
from what you'll have heard
I'm not sir
but what I have done is derelict my duty
so maybe I deserve what's coming I want
to assure you Mr Lions Holmes said that
my intention here is to uncover the
truth and uncover it I will if you are
as you say innocent of any crime you
have nothing to fear from the law but
tell me how you think you failed in your
duty what I Were Meant to keep me high
on the shipment sir weren't I I fell
asleep it's not something I make a habit
of but this time I did and woke to find
the bullion gone a nightmare sir I
suppose I should have stopped the train
with a pool call but I was in a bit of a
daze
how long do you think you slept I
thought about that sir I remember us
passing through the White Horse Valley
just before Swindon and when I woke up
we were about 10 miles out of it and
passed the lamsy water tower Holmes
looked towards the fireman mcglinchey a
plump man with Rich black curls when you
stop to fill the tank did you notice
anything odd no sir it was a dark night
and there were no lights there save the
fires from the boiler you couldn't see
20 feet beyond the train
homes turned back to Lions I would like
you to describe to me the events of
yesterday evening well sir oh I wasn't
you starting my shift until one in the
morning so around about 12 I had a brown
ale in the railway mince can eat and
collected some sandwiches and a can of
tea for the journey just tea and
sandwiches yes sir and a piece of seed
cake if that's not too much detail
there is no such thing as too much
detail please continue with your story
well at about half past one I made my
way over to the goods platform they just
finished loading the bullion into the
end carriage and the other part the
train had been brought in and coupled up
a gentleman in his suit gave us final
instructions to the engineering farm and
Tommy and Pat here he said the train was
cleared to London with just the one
brief water stop which was under no
circumstances to take more than three
minutes and if there should be an
emergency they won't leave the cab
at that point they locked me in with the
gold and at exactly 2 A.M we were on our
way
about a half hour after I had me
sandwiches and a few swigs of tea it
were a clear night and I sat by one of
the windows and watched the Stars
contented with everything sir that's
when I must have dozed and well what
happened after that you know
thank you lions
said Holmes then he turned to Young
inspector Hopkins with a new Fierce
gleam in his eye if we may Hopkins I
should now like to inspect the train
we made our way along the track to the
engine sheds and after checking the
locomotive searched through each of the
13 coaches whose number I carefully
counted myself until we arrived at the
last the guards coach in which the gold
had been transported
now I have been assured Holmes said to
Hopkins that the doors of this coach
were locked from the outside for the
duration of the journey
yes Mr ohms
yet it was possible to move along the
train through the coaches via the
connecting doors yes and what are the
other coaches
I checked them that outer doors were all
locked too but it would have been
impossible anyway for the thieves to
have moved the containers along the
train to Jefferson them from another
Carriage the boxes of gold were too big
to pass through the connecting doors all
that had been carefully calculated
but is it quite certain I ventured that
the boxes could not have been opened and
the gold removed bar by bar quite
certain said Hopkins not without the
original keys they were unique to each
box
besides Watson said Holmes if the boxes
had been opened here then with or
without the gold they would still surely
be here now
speaking of which Hopkins The Carriage
is just as it was found when the doors
were first opened this morning as I said
Mr ohms nothing's been touched
Holmes took an initial sweeping glass
around the carriage interior then
stooped to pick something up from the
floor
this brown paper I presume the wrapping
for the guard Lion's sandwiches
yes this is can of tea yes
curious that he had a can of tea
no no
curious that a man under stress should
be so painstakingly tidy I don't
understand sir
never mind what do you make of this
Hopkins
homes had picked up from the corner a
loop of scarlet fabric silken and
ruffled
I don't know Mr domes I was completely
baffled by it it seems to be a small
decorative item of some sort from a
lady's wardrobe
a hair tie I should think I said how
might it have got here
I don't know doctor I'm sure but I
suppose it's theoretically possible that
someone might have concealed herself in
another carriage
Holmes had put the object to his nose
that is a perfume to it he said but
faint as though it had not been worn for
some time
could it belong to the thief I asked
tentatively possibly said Holmes though
I think that might have been a thief too
many
he stooped to replace the Scarlet fabric
on the floor of the carriage
I think we are close to a conclusion
Watson
Hopkins I should like to talk to the
guard lands again and to the driver and
his fireman please make sure that there
is at least one other police officer
present and we must be sure to invite Mr
Benedict Masterson to our little denumor
since she's been kind enough to pay the
fee for this investigation
by the time Masterson arrived the Clock
Was approaching nine and we sat in the
old mess room bathed in dingy yellow
Gaslight the rain rattled ceaselessly on
the roof and windows and when we were
all assembled the three weary railwaymen
along with Benedict Masterson inspector
Hopkins a junior officer and Holmes and
myself
the Gathering became hushed and
expectant
Masterson said
well this has certainly been a baffling
business Mr Holmes but I assume we're
here because you've picked up some Clues
along the way
you are certainly a man equal to his
reputation sir
the inspector mentioned a red silk
trinket of some sort
yes Holmes said he produced the item
from his pocket this piece of perfumed
fabric
the clear message is that someone was
concealed in the carriage with the
bullion
I see and moreover I put in that the
concealed person was probably female
Masterson appeared a little shaken
female you say
oh dear
if I may said Holmes we will return to
that later Mr Lyons let us revert for
the present to the subject of your
sandwiches my sandwiches again sir
indeed
the sandwiches you took on board the
train last night together with the seed
cake in the can of cold tea
you say you at them just before you fell
asleep yes sir
you ate the sandwiches and the cake you
dozed off you woke up again and the gold
was gone
yes sir
that's how it happened
and when you came around and realized
the gold had gone you say it was like a
nightmare yes Mr Rose you were very
agitated I certainly was too agitated I
expect to sweep the floor of the
carriage to what sir I presume you did
not sweep the floor of the carriage at
that point in that Disturbed state
no sir I didn't with respect sir that's
not my job quite I wouldn't expect you
to which makes it very difficult to
explain why when I examined the guards
coach this afternoon I found not a
single crumb on the floor Now can anyone
here tell me how it's possible to eat
several sandwiches and a slice of seed
cake without dropping a single crumb or
come to that A Single Seed
I promise you sir what I said about my
supper was true I remember exactly what
I brought and exactly what I ate I have
no doubt of that Mr Lions then what sir
my point is merely that you were
obviously not in coach 13 when you ate
the sandwiches
On My Honor Mr Owens I swear I was oh
you weren't in a cannon certainly but
you were not in the carriage in which
your sandwich wrapper was found
the coach where you ate your supper the
coach with the bullion
never made it to London
Mr Holmes
this is confusing began Masterson homes
interrupted on the contrary Mr Masterson
it's very clear the coach containing the
gold was uncoupled from the train when
it stopped for water run into a sighting
by those awaiting it and unloaded of its
cargo at their Leisure during the night
it was a perfectly dark night there was
no moon so the railway men as Mr
mcglinchey here has recently confirmed
could from the water pump see nothing of
what was going on at the back of the
train
but Mr Holmes said inspector Hopkins the
bad luck special has 13 coaches everyone
knows that and you will no doubt
yourself and noted that we passed
through exactly 13 coaches in our
inspection of the train this afternoon
oh it has 13 coaches now of course
inspector Holmes said
and it only struck me after we had left
Bristol and its pleasant station Master
Willits that he had described to us in
detail his whole engagement with the
loading of the gold and the departure of
the train without once mentioning that
he'd counted the coaches before the
train left
the fact is he didn't count them he
didn't think he needed to the bad luck
special had always consisted of 13
coaches he wasn't to know that your
accomplices at Bristol had added an
additional coach to the train before it
was attached to the coach carrying the
boxes a coach with its seats stripped
out to make it practically identical to
the bullion car
on that one night the bad luck special
had not 13 but 14 carriages
when the train stopped to acquire water
it simultaneously shed a coach and it
very nearly he continued turning back to
Lions shared a guard too
you're a very fortunate man lions
I don't feel fortunate sir
your good fortune is that you are still
alive and that in turn is because you
are fortunate enough to fall asleep
imagine if you had not the train stops
the thieves uncouple the rear coach with
yourself inside it as soon as you see
them you become a risk to them there's
no telling what they might have done
what I believe actually happened was
that as they were releasing The Carriage
from the train someone noticed that you
were asleep inside they took the
opportunity to move you into the next
coach along with your tea can and
sandwich wrappings
you may be thankful you did not wake at
that moment
Masterson War an expression of amazement
I am full of admiration Mr Holmes
but at the same time I feel somewhat
desolated
this clearly means that someone in my
organization has betrayed me
which brings me back to the Ring of
scarlet silk discovered in the cottage
certainly an intriguing adornment to the
problem said Holmes
it could indeed signify the presence of
a woman
but there is the mystery I said of how
she got there or what she might have
done
I think however said Holmes that is a
mystery with a simple solution
at this point Masterson appeared rather
tragically stricken you're thinking
yes said Holmes you're thinking that my
estranged wife Laura
dear God that foolish woman oh come
along Mr Masterson you know full well
your wife had nothing to do with it
there was no one aboard the train saved
the three men here driver engineer and
guard and none of them had anything to
do with the robbery
the three railwaymen looked at one
another as though they had suddenly had
revealed to them their entitlement to a
joint Fortune
as for the thieves said Holmes they are
to be located somewhere nursing a horde
of bullying a part of course from their
paymaster who is sitting here with us
is that not so Mr Masterson
Masterson blasted and steamed he was
outraged this was absurd
how dare you sir what evidence have you
for such an outrageous suggestion I had
misgivings from the beginning I could
not understand why you came to me so
quickly after the theft had been
discovered when you had so much else to
deal with
I see now that you were pains to
demonstrate to the insurance company
that you were doing all in your power to
recover the bullion because of course if
you could have both the gold and the
insurance money you would have
considerably augmented your fortune
but worse still
what your partners in crime would have
done to Mr Lions had he not had the good
sense to fall asleep on the job hardly
Bears thinking about
you were prepared not just to steal but
to be an accessory to murder this is
speculation Mr Holmes this would not
stand up in court you should be looking
for another felon what about that red
silk ring ah yes
you've been very subtle about that Mr
Masterson
suggesting your wife's name one moment
and the next assuring me that she could
not possibly be implicated
I doubt whether you thought she would be
but you certainly sought to throw me off
the scent
what was that item if not a red herring
and is that not for those who like to
play games with words another way to say
a red heading
what fun you no doubt plan to have with
that joke Mr Masterson had you got away
with this business
now it seems The Joke is on You
that was one pun Mr Masterson
which you would indeed have done better
to have resisted
but whether Justice was fully done is a
moot point in expectation of reducing
his own sentence Masterson eventually it
divulged the names of his accomplices
and led police to the embezzled bullion
and although he was committed to prison
for several years it was clear that once
his sentence was served he would
continue the life of a wealthy man
can't understand I said to Holmes a
couple of evenings later why you seem so
damnably happy
a man is never more content Watson he
said than when doing well what his
Nature has fitted him to do
a witch thought will you pass me the
tobacco pouch
I think we should indulge ourselves in a
brace of good pipes
[Music]
the Trinity vicarage larceny
One Fine spring morning Sherlock Holmes
and I received into our rooms a portly
gentleman in a purple dress
that at least is how it momentarily
appeared to me as I glanced up from the
Daily Chronicle at the open door
the purple gentleman it transpired was
the right Reverend the Lord Bishop of
Kent an old acquaintance of homes and he
had brought with him as so many of our
visitors do a problem that was clearly
causing him some agitation
mollified a little by coffee and a cigar
Bishop Spriggs needed no prompting to
divulge his story
the knob of my problem gentlemen is an
unfortunate young priest
a young man of promise and talent very
popular with his parishioners who has
inadvertently got himself into deep
water
intriguing said Holmes
you may recall the clergyman continued
the Trinity Church in the Kent Village
of hechingham was last year in the news
because of an exceptional discovery of
course I said a silver chalice of
considerable worth was discovered in the
Crypt yes Dr Watson a magnificent
medieval Relic the so-called hatchingham
Grail weighing some 22 pounds with my
approval it was sold to the British
museum with the idea that a good portion
of the proceeds would go towards
restoring hatchingham Church
the Reverend Kingsley pending the
beginning of the building work had
locked the money up in the church Crypt
it was stolen yesterday
Holmes you can imagine what an outcry
they'd be if this found its way into the
papers it would be bad for Kingsley and
the hatching comparish and goodness and
limb knows what it would do for the
repetition of the church
at any cost the money must be recovered
and the thief put away
and I mean any cost homes let us not
concern ourselves with fees just yet
home said
are there any clues at all as to who
might be responsible for this theft I'm
not sure about Clues replied to
clergyman Kingsley did make some sort of
an attempt to discover the identity of
the villain by chasing him over the
fields after the theft but I'm afraid he
didn't get very far
I think we had better meet the young
Reverend said Holmes as soon as is
practical Watson would you be at Liberty
to accompany meter hatching him for a
few days
I'm utterly indebted to you both said
the bishop I dare say while you're in
hatching him we could put you up at the
Trinity Church wreck today oh there's
the Jolly Bulldog if you'd prefer an in
ah said Holmes that Jolly Bulldog now
that sounds like just my kind of animal
we journeyed to hatchingham the next
morning and established ourselves at the
Cozy but crumbling hostility that was
the Jolly bulldog
our landlord was a bluff man called
Starkey taller by inches than Holmes and
compelled to stoop to avoid the beams of
his own ceiling as he lumbered about in
heavy boots serving his customers
he grudgingly provided us with a late
snack of bread and some rather tough
cold meats complaining that if everyone
chose to be fed at half past two in the
afternoon they would have to invent a
new word for the meal taken between
luncheon and dinner
leftovers said Holmes to me impishly and
at a level which I am sure Starkey was
meant to overhear might be that word
the public and growled ominously as he
left us and I leaned over to Holmes and
whispered there is surely an example of
how a little power may go to the head of
a man and make him too big for his boots
I was thinking rather said Holmes from
the way he clumps about this place that
his boots are rather too big for him
I saw the two gentlemen on a nearby
table smile at this remark
I shouldn't take a lot of notice of
Starkey said one of them amiibly he's
just as tiresome with all the customers
the gentleman introduced himself as John
hapten and His companion as Matthew
Winslow although neither Holmes nor
myself disclosed the details of our
mission to hatching him it seems they
knew we were expected and it turned out
that both gentlemen were members of the
parish committee and were fully apprised
of the theft though they were quick to
assert that it was not yet public
knowledge I hope you will be successful
said Hampton in bringing this thief to
book we Are fond of our vegan and he has
been a deeply troubled young man since
it happened
the Reverend kingsley's house was
accessed from hatchingham Lane by a
short Stone path
a few steps beyond the vicarage stood
the church with on the West Side a
moderate-sized graveyard on the other
side with its own access to the Lane and
shaded by a handful of fruit trees stood
Cherry cottage which we would later
discover to be the residents of The
Verge and his wife
the Reverend Kingsley was a man in his
early 30s small in stature but of good
looks his clerical dress the Quint
essence of neatness
while clearly stricken by his
predicament he remained calm and
articulate and did his best to make us
welcome in a pleasantly appointed parlor
whose deep colored thick piled carpet
and embroidered cushions evidenced a
delicate sense of taste
it's a relief to see you gentlemen he
said the bishop told me all about you
about your many successes in solving
complex cases
the problem as you know is that while we
saw the thief Escape we were unable to
establish his identity however there are
one or two factors which that they seem
opaque to my own consideration might
prove Illuminating under your own if I
might show you
I would be most grateful Mr Kingsley
Holmes said first though I see that you
have recently held a meeting in this
charming room I presume that apart from
the three other gentlemen present the
fourth was yourself
you keep the side chairs in another room
I take it
how did you know all that
oh it's a simple matter the carpet
beside the window has indentations of
four chairs and therefore I presume four
four people but there are no chairs in
the room whose feet would match well yes
you are of course quite correct said
Kingsley with a broad smile the parish
committee convened here just yesterday
as we do each week
yesterday was the day I broke the news
that the Grail money had been stolen and
I hope that that news will remain privy
to the committee members until such time
as the thief is caught but
the vicar paused and Holmes said please
go on Mr Kingsley
but continued the young clergyman the
gentleman on the parish committee are
the same three who sat here two weeks
ago
when I revealed that the money for the
Grail was in the Crypt of the church
only they and I knew of the fact you see
so I can no longer be as confident as
before that they are all honest men
which is a most unfortunate thing
it was all in cash I presume home said
yes Mr Holmes I kept cash so that I
could employ local men to restore the
church and pay them by the day I have
little time to run to the bank and make
a withdrawal every time a man finishes
Plastering a wall
the money was under lock and key
yes there is a safe in the Crypt where
the church's small Treasures have always
been secreted
and the Crypt itself is locked yes it
can be entered either from within the
church or by a door leading from the
churchyard and both those doors are
locked at night
Mr Holmes
I do hope you can help me with this
I don't know how my flock will ever
forgive me if that money is not returned
then perhaps if you can bear to go over
it all again you would be so kind as to
tell Dr Watson and myself the
circumstances of the robbery
yes of course
two weeks ago looking out of this window
on a Monday morning at about 11 I saw a
man
I'm fairly certain it was a man standing
at the Lich gate and looking over into
the chair chart
I would not have given this a moment's
thought except that he wore a hat with
an unusually wide brim and had it pulled
so low over his eyes and his collar so
high that one could not distinguish his
features
as I say I cannot even be certain was
not a woman
except for his way of moving
I watched him for a good 10 minutes
before he turned and Strode back along
the lane towards the village
that same afternoon this time from an
upstairs window I saw him again but now
further along the lane standing under a
tree and once again seeming to study the
church and its grounds
his contrived anonymity naturally put me
on my guard
in the evening after those first two
sightings I was sitting in that very
chair Dr Watson which you are currently
occupying when a thought hit me like a
bolt of lightning I thought which you no
doubt will be surprised had not occurred
to me earlier
that this stranger might have designs on
the money in the Crypt
after this alarming Epiphany I spoke to
my Verger Sam manners and his wife may
who keep house for me they live in
Cherry cottage which as you will have
seen stands on the lane beside the
church's Lich gate
there's a shortcut from their back door
to this house which they employ when
they wish to see me I mentioned that
because as I think you would agree it
Bears upon the matter
I asked them to report to me if this
Sinister figure or anyone else unknown
to them appeared in the vicinity of the
church
and indeed it seems as if the man in
that hat had begun to watch my
whereabouts because first May manners
then her husband reported to me that
they had indeed seen the man in the Hat
I began to feel that an attempt on the
money was imminent
I resolved then to remain in the
vicarage or the church grounds until I
was certain that the threat had passed
I instructed Mr and Mrs manners that if
they saw the stranger again they were to
take the shortcut to my house and inform
me immediately but they were under no
circumstances to approach him
and now we come to the day of the theft
Sam manners was whitewashing the walls
of the church
at this point Holmes stood up
I think it would be as well Mr Kingsley
to acquaint ourselves with the geography
of the church and its grounds
might we continue outside
a rapturous afternoon of sunshine and
Birdsong greeted us as we left the
vicarage and walked out into the
churchyard where the Reverend Kingsley
commenced our guided tour
I immediately began to locate us on a
mental map of hatchingham village and
its surrounding areas a practice I
learned in my Military Days in which has
served me well in civilian life I could
see in my mind the large oblong of
Farmland about two miles across with
hatchingham Village and the church
almost at opposite corners
this substantial area of land was
surrounded on all four sides by public
roads
Mr Kingsley took us through the grounds
on a grassy path which ran along the
side of the church up against the
gravestones of the churchyard
this is the wall of the church Sarah
manners was painting that morning said
the vicar
he worked for a couple of hours and at
12 o'clock I sent him off to his cottage
for his regular midday meal I went back
into the vicarage and took up a book
after about 20 minutes there was a knock
at the back door
Mrs manners was in a frantic State she
and Sam had just seen the man in the
white brimmed hat going into the church
hat I told her to return immediately and
to tell Sam to meet me here at the
crypto and I came here directly to find
myself staring at a spectacular mess
he pointed to a flight of four steps
just off the path leading to a door low
down in the half-painted church wall
the door to the Crypt he said from which
the thief must have made his exit and
not expecting to encounter a paint
bucket presumably kicked it flying in
his haste to escape
a residual expanse of powdery white
still damp in places stained the
flagstones at the bottom of the steps
Sam was with me within seconds continued
the vicar we could see nobody but we
soon guessed which way he'd gone
if you're following me gentlemen the
vicar led us a little further along the
grassy path to where the churchyard
ended in a wooden fence set into the
fence was a style leading onto a
footpath
that said the vicar was his Escape Route
beyond the style the Ragged footpath
traversed the meadow through weeds and
rough grasses stretching away into the
distance along this narrow track could
be seen intermittent Blobs of white
and I suppose the presumption would be
said Holmes that the trail of white
paint marks are the fleeing man's
footsteps yes exactly obviously our man
escaped across the field to Harding Lane
Mr Holmes my companion nodded he stopped
at the style
that are two white handprints here he
said a right hand and a left hand
the fellows in some haste as indeed one
would expect
Holmes crossed the style athletically
and walked a little way into the field
bending down he examined one of the
white marks then plucked up a handful of
grass and returned to us
thank you Mr Kingsley I think I've seen
all I need to hear is there anything
else you think might help us yes said
the vicar enthusiastically back at the
house
Holmes requested that Sam manners and
his wife join us in the vicarage and a
little afterwards in Mr kingsley's
kitchen Mrs manners set herself to the
task of making us all tea while Holmes
paced the stone floor slowly
I sat at the kitchen table with the
vicar and Sam manners and Ruddy man in
his early 40s whom Holmes was now
addressing
so Mr manners you are the only person to
have caught a glimpse of the man in the
Hat on the day of the robbery I believe
so sir I was at the window taking my
lunch I saw this fellow in the Big Air
looking up and down the lane a few times
as if to check all was clear then enter
over the churchyard
straight away I said to me it's his
Manos to go by the back door and tell
the vicar and you yourself waited in the
cottage until Mrs manners returned I did
Sir
for how long not more than two minutes
she told me the vicar wanted me to meet
him out by the church I Dash right out
and found the Reverend Kingsley waiting
for you yeah sure and the door to the
wide open whitewash everywhere hmm
the crypt door had been locked before
you went to lunch oh yes Mr Holmes it
always was and that was when you noticed
the trail of paint exactly sir and set
off to follow it you must have only been
a short way behind the thief
must have been Sarah but he moved Like
the Wind
we was across that Meadow in less than
five minutes it's good four furlongs and
never caught up to him
but what we found at the opposite side
clinched it
here Mr Kingsley interrupted Sam means
this he said and produced from a draw a
wide brimmed black velvet hat
inexpensively made and in shape rather
resembling the sort of thing one sees
worn by picadors in pictures of
bullfights Holmes took the hat and
turned it around in his hands it was me
found it sir said manners I was running
a bit ahead of the Reverend open to
catch up with our thief and as soon as I
was over the style I saw it in the grass
by the road just where I suppose it had
fallen from his head well said Holmes
while I cannot see yet how that will
help us with your permission I shall
take it away with me
of course
said to Vicar we'll leave you then but
by way of that path across the fields
I'd rather like to follow the route
taken by our escaping felon
and so it was that we made our farewells
and set out from the church out across
the wide Meadow towards Harding Lane
although it had been a week since the
church Thief had fled there remained a
clear trail of white Footprints across
the entire width of the field
the path ended at another style which
gave onto the Shaded narrowness of
Harding Lane
we calculated that the return to
hatching a village we could go in either
direction around the perimeter of the
meadow we took the route West along the
pincham road rather than going east and
back via the church
as we walked my companion looked
repeatedly this way and that into the
fields at the roadside the patches of
scrubland and the bushes and trees
if you note anything you must let me
know Watson and I agreed that I would
but the fields lay bright and innocent
in the late afternoon air and the trees
were populated only by birds jubilantly
enjoying the sunshine
then as we cross the bridge over a
gurgling stream homes stopped halfway
there's something there do you see he
pointed to the bank of the stream above
which a Hawthorne overhung the Rushing
Water something that bush
a pair of some things unless I'm
mistaken
we clambered over the baddestrate of the
little bridge and dropped onto the bank
side
the Hawthorne was thick and even at
Close Quarters my eyes were at panes to
penetrate into its depths Holmes using a
fallen Branch the thickness of his arm
smashed his way into the bush his soft
Cry of Triumph told me he had found
something and he reached in and
retrieved in one hand a large pair of
leather boots
what do you think Watson is this or is
this not the Footwear of our Thief
they're certainly large those of a very
big man I should say
and that a white marks on the souls
should we see how they fit those prints
on the church Meadow
I think we can assume that much Watson
but what would induce the villain to
Jesus in his boots here perhaps I said
he thought he was still being chased and
knew that if he were caught wearing them
he would be recognized straight away
equally suspicious if he'd been found
with no boots at all said Holmes though
I suppose he may have carried a spare
pair of shoes with him Watson it is
fairly clear to me the thief is a local
man why unless he feared to be
recognized would he indulge in such an
elaborate disguise
let us go back to the Jolly Bulldog that
after all is where the locals like to
congregate
in fact on our return to the Inn we
found John Hampton and Matthew Winslow
the parish committee men we had met
earlier having returned to or perhaps
never having left the same table
as we sat down Holmes placed beside him
on the floorboards the pair of boots we
had found in the Hedgerow causing the
two gentlemen to look at them
inquisitively
when Starkey the landlord arrived to
service the first thing he said was your
boats gentlemen not ours said Holmes we
found them in a bush in Harding Lane
strange what some folks will throw away
said the public and they looks in Prime
order to me
hardly been worn Holmes replied and then
he asked would these boots fit you Mr
Starkey and seeing our companions on the
nearby table watching he added
or either of you gentlemen not me sir
Starkey replied rather more amiably than
I had expected
I know my boots look way e but my feet
and it's a big as you might think it's
just I'm subject to blisters
could you find big boots help your
blisters I asked my experience of
patients suffering with that condition
telling me the opposite no sir to start
the blisters I need to put on three
pairs of thick hose so always gets my
boots well over in my proper foot size
then rather sardonically he said
thank you though for asking sir
Mr Hampton on the next table asked
what's your interest in Boots Holmes
said it's an investigation we are
conducting in which boots have well some
scientific significance
then to me he whispered as our neighbor
turned away with a disbelieving grimace
as I thought Watson we have our culprit
Starkey no not Starkey one of these
and I indicated with my thumb the two
men from the parish committee oh Watson
who then these boots Watson Do You
observe nothing untoward about them
no not at all the practically knew that
of a large size apart from that they are
undistinguished
on the contrary my friend I would say
they were distinguished by a lack of
paint a baker pardon I mean Watson that
there are white marks on the souls to be
sure but tell me pray have a man with
his hands covered in whitewash could
have unlaced and removed his boots
without leaving marks on the laces I
don't know I said but it would be a
singular coincidence if someone
completely innocent had jettisoned a
pair of boots with paint on the Soles
there is no coincidence Holmes said
These boots were undoubtedly left here
by the thief but not in the way we were
intended to believe are you suggesting
that you know who the thief is
the thief Watson is the reverent
Kingsley himself
how could it be homes there was no time
for him to escape across that Meadow and
return to the vicarage in time to meet
Sam manners outside the church How could
a man Chase himself across a meadow
as you know Watson we are due to meet
the bishop this evening at Trinity
vicarage
so let us finish our meal I will explain
everything there
we had promised the bishop an interim
meeting at the vicarage to advise him of
our progress in the case which no doubt
the clergyman expected to be only
moderate this soon after our previous
meeting but we had hardly settled to our
Sherry in Mr kingsley's comfortable
parlor then Holmes declared dramatically
you will no doubt be delighted to know
gentlemen that Dr Watson and I have
solved the case
I did not think of my business to
confess that after my previous
conversation with Holmes I was as much
in the dark as anyone but I sat quietly
sipping my Shetty while I watched my
friend open the bag we had brought from
the inn and removed the two large white
stained boots we had found beside the
Stream
The Bishop's eyes widened
I have to say he looked incredulous
Mr Kingsley too wore a skeptical smirk
and raised his eyebrows please tell us
Mr Holmes what you think you have found
Dr Watson and I found these Holmes
explained in a bramble bush in Harding
Lane
big boots suggested we were seeking a
big man yet the footprints told us his
stride was short
it was our landlord at the Jolly Bulldog
who enabled me to understand the
dichotomy he is a man who buys bigger
boots than his foot size in order to
accommodate extra socks our villain
however bought his bigger boots in order
to accommodate another pair of shoes
leaving the footprints of a bigger man
than he is himself
is that not so Mr Kingsley
the young vicar I thought at the time if
he was guilty of anything
was heroically cool about it
he betrayed nothing but gentile's
surprise
are you suggesting that I was the thief
Mr hobbed
Holmes said the bishop Gravely
from what I understand Mr Kingsley and
his Verger practically managed to catch
up with the thief on that fateful day
what on Earth do you think is the
evidence for this assertion
my Lord Holmes said confidently Mr
Kingsley wished to embezzle the money
raised by the sale of the hatchingham
Grail and decided to construct a piece
of Theater which would deceive
investigators he not only invented the
spectral man and the large brimmed hat
he also on several occasions paraded in
the Hat in the high collared coat and
ensured that Mr and Mrs manners caught a
glimpse of him on the day of the theft
having sent Sam manners to lunch he came
back here to the vicarage assumed the
disguise showed himself at the cottage
window where manners was eating and
proceeded into the churchyard
dashing back to the vicodage again he
slipped out of his cloak and hat and
waited for Mrs manners knock on the door
he told Mrs manners to summon her
husband and rendezvous with him outside
the crypt door and then what said Mr
Kingsley insolent with Fury I put on
these boots unlocked the church went
down to the Crypt took the money escaped
the church jumped the style and ran
across a mile at the field then dashed a
mile back took off the boots and waited
calmly for Sam to arrive whereupon I
went chasing off across the field again
that would indeed have been ingenious to
do in two minutes what an athlete could
not do in 20. yes indeed the question as
my friend Dr Watson has clarified is
precisely how may a man Chase himself
across a meadow
and the answer asked the bishop
no one will ever know at what point you
took the money Mr Kingsley
as the keyhole that you are free to do
it at your leisure and for all one knows
it may never have been in the Crypt safe
in the first place certainly there was
no need for you to waste time on it on
the day we are discussing you wished to
ensure there was just enough time with
Mr manners at lunch for you to get to
the crypto and kick over the white wash
bucket and of course you had given Mr
Manus the task of whitewashing that
particular part of the church wall
simply to ensure that there would be a
bucket there to be upturned
that was all you needed to do because
and here is the thing you had made the
footprints across the field on the night
before
you would also I have no doubt planted
the boots in the Hedgerow on the same
occasion making sure they had plenty of
white paint on the Soles foolishly you
forgot to dorb a little on the shoe
laces
at this point the vicar dropped into a
chair as though all resistance had
suddenly fled him
and I believe that as Holmes proceeded
we all realized that he was now
approaching a devastating conclusion at
some out of that night Mr Kingsley
having splashed so much whitewash on the
underside of the boots that your hands
were gloved with paint you planted your
white printed Trail along the footpath
across the meadow to Harding Lane
afterwards you dropped the wide brimmed
hat by the style and jettisoned the
boots in a bush further along Harding
Lane
the trail of Prince was therefore neatly
in place for the deception next morning
and I dare say you were solicitors to
keep Mr manners away from the style
where he might prematurely stumble upon
your if I may so miss name it handiwork
but one moment said the bishop
if Mr Kingsley had dropped the Hat the
night before how could he have been
wearing it that morning
well of course that's simple said Holmes
there were two hats and finally there
was the question of the keys what
question was that Holmes I asked I don't
recollect any mention of keys
precisely
there was a distinct absence of any such
mention why because a key would have
been needed to enter the Crypt and Mr
Kingsley thought it better not to raise
the tricky matter of how such an
intruder might have got hold of one
the pale face and slumped figure of Mr
Kingsley indicated his utter defeat
the bishop clearly needed no further
convincing
the money Kingsley
he said
have you spent it
the vicar looked bitter
I'm a gambler Bishop
and the truth is that over the years I
have burdened myself with appalling debt
I started to use the church money bit by
bit I meant to return it one day when I
had a big win but
money runs through my hands like water
there's little of it left
then it's a matter for the police
the bishop said
and we must find a new vicar for
hatching them
I fear that you Mr Kingsley will for
many years be the incumbent of a much
dingier perish
[Music]
the 1059 assassin
it is now well known that the
investigations of my friend and
companion Sherlock Holmes which I have
had the privilege to document over the
years represent only a small portion of
his life's work
many other cases have fallen into the
Obscure well of history
but nothing departs this world without
leaving some trace or memory and now and
then an old story rears its head so it
was with the events of the stovey murder
A letter came to Holmes one morning at
our Baker Street Department from Samuel
Carpenter an elderly Publican at the
horse in colors hostery in the Kent
Village of stovy
several years previously Samuel
Carpenter had been a witness at the
trial of Arthur weeks a local villain
accused of intimidation abduction
blackmail and Grievous bodily harm
Holmes had been involved in helping
police on the case with footprint
evidence and thus had come to meet the
amiable publican
I suppose we never expected to visit the
quatt settlement of stovey ever again
but the letter contained a clear and
Urgent summons
Dear Mr Holmes
you did say when we made our fell Wells
four years ago that if ever there should
be a day when I had need of your
assistance I was to write to you
immediately I'm afraid sir
that day has come
a terrible set of events has clouded my
life and I am quite a loss
Arthur wakes that ruthless villain you
hoped put away died in jail a few months
ago
ever since then his son Henry has been
making our lives a misery
I found my dog catcher shot dead in the
field
and twice a dead fox in our water tank
started getting letters threatening to
burn down the Inn telling me I should
one day wait in vain for my wife to come
home terrible things but all written
anonymous
then he brazenly come and drink at the
end as innocent as you like
well last week our son jack told weeks
straight there in front of all my
customers
that he'd gone too far and he'd better
prepare himself for some serious
consequences I wish she had not done it
two days afterwards weeks was found
shocked through the head and my Jack is
now being arrested as a murderer
there's anything you may be able to do
Mr ohms
please come immediately
I knew that Holmes had taken strongly to
the public and so it was hardly a
surprise to me when he asked as is his
way whether I had any pressing
engagements over the next few days and
when I said no instructed me to pack
immediately an overnight bag within an
hour we were aboard a Kent bound train
in stovey Village we took rooms at the
horse in colors and as soon as we were
settled in sat with our landlord at a
table in the bar where a large fire
battled the chill in the air
Holmes said
now Mr Carpenter
the first thing you must do if I'm to
help you is to answer my questions
honestly and accurately
that I will do Mr Holmes
your Jack made a threat to Henry weeks
here in this bar yes sir and two days
later weeks was found dead dead with a
shot through his head just outside the
village where Nightingale Lane crosses
the London Railway line and his horse
tied up nearby and they came to arrest
Jack when that very night but Jack
wasn't here of course wasn't here Jack
couldn't have killed him Mr ohms Jack
was already aboard the London train when
weeks was killed
it was offered by himself a suit for his
wedding
I took him to stovey station myself that
evening to catch the 10 59. there were a
moment when Jack left my sight I watched
him get on that train and waved him off
as it left
but the police didn't seem to think that
counts for anything
as soon as he got back here next day
they carted him off and he's now on the
lock and key in Maidstone jail
well Mr Carpenter said Holmes I accept
unequivocally that what you are telling
me is the truth but my sense is that
this is going to be a very convoluted
business and I must impress on you the
need to be patient
when Carpenter had returned to serving
his customers I said quietly to Holmes
surely if what the old chap says is true
the police have no case weeks must have
had a hundred enemies hungry for his
blood with thought we could Alibis than
Jack Carpenter
perhaps so said Holmes but I fear the
word of a father in defense of a son is
unlikely to be regarded in quarters
compelling evidence especially when the
police have their minds made up in
advance
Watson I have a suspicion that things
may get a lot more obscure before they
become clearer let's make good use of
the afternoon by acquainting ourselves
with the details of Henry week's
unfortunate end
our escort to the scene of the crime was
a local policeman Sergeant Berry a man
of stubborn practicality whose uniform
one suspected must have been artfully
augmented to accommodate the spectacular
retundity of his belly
he clearly felt he had better things to
do than to accompany a Consulting
detective to the scene of a crime when
the culprit was already halfway to The
Gallows
walking from stovey Village we arrived
at a spot about 30 yards from a level
crossing where the main London Railway
line traversed Nightingale Lane
dark Hill Crossing co-ops found here
Sergeant Betty said bluntly six feet
from the fence victims are still tied to
defense cause of death single bullet
entering just here
he put a plump finger in the center of
his brow
weapon a gun said the policeman
insolently I am aware said Holmes
clearly irritated that if a man is
killed with a bullet then the probable
source of the missile is a firearm what
I want to know is whether the weapon has
been found or if not whether anyone has
deduced the type of gun from the type of
bullet
no gun found said Betty as for the
bullet as far as I know it's still at
the end of a short tunnel into his skull
and the horse oh I don't think we can
pin it on the horse sir the policeman
said with a smirk
Sergeant Berry Holmes was threateningly
patient are you able to assist me in
this investigation or would it be more
convenient to you if I were to apply to
my acquaintances at the yard to find me
an alternative guide
the policeman looked suddenly chastened
just my joke Mr Holmes yes I can take
you to the horse sir
and to the body
we saw the horse first it had been
stabled with the police horses in a yard
in the village a tall brown stallion
with rather frightened eyes when young
it must have been a formidable creature
now it looked ragged from a lifetime of
hard riding Holmes looked it over
carefully the animal was skittish
seemingly distressed and tried to pull
away when Holmes held its Bridle to
examine its head
I watched rather nervously as my friend
entered the stable Bay and walked around
the animal which threatened to jostle
him against the walls
then when he reached the front of the
creature again home said
there's a Mark here a sharp wound can
you see
on the right foreleg just above the
fetlock joint was a slender but quite
noticeable lesion apparently caused
fairly recently
Holmes turned to Betty again
was this Mark here when the horse was
found I believe so
good well since we seem to be in the
business of investigating wounds today
you'd better show us the way to the
morgue incidentally Sergeant how well do
you know the accused man
fairly well replied the policeman
do you know whether he has friends
acquaintances perhaps of some intimacy
well not really that I know of so
it was always at his father's public
house and they were ever a close lot I
mean the sergeant Betty stopped he
became instantly animated and
business-like a gleam came into his eyes
and he said look there's the military
missed Rome's just after the church I'll
leave you to it if I may just thought of
something rather urgent I've got to do
and very briskly almost running he
disappeared back towards the village
strange I said to Holmes what do you
think that was about
I think said Holmes that I've put an
idea into his head I only hope it
doesn't complicate matters
it transpired that a postmortem on the
dead man had been commissioned but that
the police pathologist had only arrived
from London that morning possibly on the
same train as Holmes and myself
I knew Professor Yardley a little
through my connection with Saint Mary's
Hospital in Paddington and he was quite
amenable to my assisting him with the
matter in hand
he was a conscientious practitioner and
while the cause of death seemed evident
he thoroughly inspected the
externalities of the corpse before
opening it the head wound was a clean
almost star-shaped hole glutted with
dried blood
there was no wound on the back of the
head and it was apparent that the bullet
had not exited the body
notwithstanding that there was no weapon
at the scene Holmes said suicide seems
out of the question wouldn't you say
that a no Powder Burns to the skin and
besides the wound is probably too small
for a close shot
I'd say the missile came from some
distance
the bullet had it turned out penetrated
the brow and lodged deep in the parietal
lobe of the brain but as Holmes had
suggested the hole in the skull was
small and there was not the dramatic
shattering of bone one might have
expected from a close shot suicide
Professor Yardley concurred was not a
possibility
we are certainly looking for a murderer
then I commented to Holmes as we
wandered back towards stovey well
somebody killed Henry weeks for certain
Watson but I have to confess that at
this moment I have no idea who it was
you didn't think we might be wrong about
Jack Carpenter after all
I do hope not Watson it would be an
appalling tragedy but then I suppose for
one poor soul or another murder always
is
hoped that our next Port of Call would
be the horse in colors for an icy wind
had blown up and I was ready for a glass
of beer and the comfort of the Inns
blazing logs
but Holmes walked us straight to stovey
station where he said we must make an
important call I stealed myself against
the increasing cold as the last Light
feeded from the sky
the station Master at stovey was Milton
Fraser a man dressed to give the
impression of order and precision his
cap fitting perfectly the balding sphere
of a small neat head and a fine silver
pocket watch peeping from his waistcoat
pocket Holmes whose own knowledge of the
country's Railways is second to none one
his confidence easily
I wish to ask you Mr Fraser he said
about yesterday evening there is a late
train to London I believe
the 1059 sir it was on time it was as it
generally is not much traffic on the
tracks at that hour
and do you recall whether any passengers
boarded the train at stovy course Adusa
Young Jack Carpenter
just him yes sir his father saw him
aboard I watched the train pull away
myself and there is no way anyone could
have left the train after that while not
here in the station no not without my
seeing him not in the station no
I suppose it might be possible for
someone to alight at the Crossing the
level crossing
yes sir the 1059 always stops a dark
Hill Crossing for a few minutes safety
precautions are Thornley bridge over the
star is considered unsafe for two trains
until they finish the repairs so the
1059 uptrend must wait until the 1104
down has come through
and this happens every night can't
recollect when it lasts didn't sir
lastly Mr Fraser can you recall which
part of the train Mr Carpenter boarded
second compartment of the third
character I'm quite sure of that
thank you Mr Fraser you've been more
helpful than you know
I suppose we now have to consider I said
to my companion back at the horse in
colors as I stared into the Flames of
the fire
the Jack Carpenter shot Henry weeks from
the stationary train we must considered
it certainly yet I think it rather
unlikely
how would Carpenter have known his
intended target was going to be waiting
there at the Crossing
then what is the significance of the
stopping train has it any
I'm beginning to think it has but I must
confess to being currently unsure in
what way
well
let's eat and then sleep on it I said
but at that moment our cozy evening was
horribly interrupted a young woman hair
disheveled came screaming into the bar
Mr Carpenter Mr Carpenter the elderly
landlord came rushing in from the
kitchen what is it Sarah it's Beth
Miller they've taken her in her who's
taken her the police that Sergeant
berries arrested her says he found a gun
what's this Pride homes who is Beth
Miller
Beth is my son Jax betrothed Carpenter
said their wedding is fixed for next
month
Beth's a good and honest young woman and
gentler as a lamb I'll see that blasted
policeman Holmes barred his way and put
a hand on his shoulder if I'm to help
you Mr Carpenter he said staring hard
into the man's wild eyes believe me when
I say that it will not serve our
purposes to be too precipitous Dr Watson
and I will go straight to the police
station and find out what's happening I
beg of you to do nothing before you hear
from us
having received Carpenter's assurances
we made our way out of stovey to the
police station a thick walled Stone
building halfway along to the next
Village once a brewery it now had the
Grim air of a medieval lock-up it would
not be exaggerating to say that my
friend and I received a cool welcome
from Sergeant Betty whose domain this
appeared to be
yes sir I do have a young woman in
custody here and I can confirm that she
has been charged on suspicion of murder
and can you tell me said Holmes how she
is supposed to have committed this crime
well obviously sir we don't know all the
details yet but with a bit of
imagination an intelligent person might
construe that she had lured Mr weeks to
Nightingale Lane on some shall we say
enticing pretext Lane and wait for him
and dispatched him with the bullet as he
tethered his horse and said Holmes would
this same intelligent person construe
that Jack Carpenter had a part in this
well yes sir that person assuming he was
using his faculties would conclude that
quite obviously Jack Carpenter was an
accessory before the fact and therefore
equally culpable
thank you Sergeant Holmes said for
simplifying what I in my sluggishness of
Mind had considered a mystifying problem
might it be possible for us to see the
prisoner now I'm sorry sir I couldn't
permit that or should it wait until I
have received Authority from my good
friend superintendent whales at the yard
the policeman licked his lips pretended
to consult a piece of paper on his desk
and said
well as you say you are or a friend of
the superintendent sir I'm sure five
minutes wouldn't hurt
we were shown to a cavernous room where
rusted iron remnants of the Brew House
remained bolted to the walls and ceiling
a large Skylight had been set with bars
and there were no other windows
a pretty dark-haired girl of no more
than 20 years sat at a wooden table
she reacted to us with suspicion as we
were admitted but no sooner had the
Constable left us alone with her and no
doubt largely in desperation she
confided in US readily
Miss Miller we have a limited amount of
time Holmes said to her and you must
tell us everything you can about this
business yes sir I'll try I think I may
have done something foolish sir
foolish I think I were the first to find
the body sir you see well now said
Holmes
I had certainly not guessed that I plan
to see my Jack onto the London train she
continued but we was held back at the
farm delivering a calf and I knew I was
likely to miss him the train usually
stops by dark heel Crossing so I thought
if I cut a long Nightingale Lane I might
be able to wave him off
but when I got there the train was
already disappearing across the bridge
then
a stone strobe from the track I saw a
horse tied up to the fence and something
on the road beside it
when I got up close I saw who it was
Henry weeks covered in blood and next to
him the gun and you picked up the gun I
asked yes sir why why did you not go
directly to the police well sir because
I recognized the gun I meant to hide it
somewhere
it were Jack's gun you see
I failed to conceal my shock
Jack's gun
so you took the gun home said because
you thought Jack Carpenter might have
killed weeks yes sir
that was my fear even though Jack was on
the train
I didn't know how long week said Lane
there sir to
it's a lonely place and he might have
been there for hours
so that didn't look good for Jack
departing as he did the very same
evening
I weren't sure of nothing Mr rhones
except that Jack was likely to get the
blame everyone knowing about the Venom
between him and the Week's family
and what home said did you do with
Jack's gun wrapped it in Marshall slung
it on my shoulder and took it home to
hide it
but I was unlucky on the way I passed
Sergeant Berry uh I think he must
afterwards have puzzled over my strange
burden for he came today to search the
cottage and that's when I was arrested
hopes I said if the murder weapon was
beside the body doesn't that at least
establish Jack's innocence unfortunately
not Watson the Assumption we had made
was that the murder occurred while Jack
was on the train if it happened well
before that I fear that either he or
Miss Miller here remained the primer
Facey Suspects but I didn't kill Henry
weeks sir I I swear to God I don't
believe you did Miss Miller but we have
to convince the police of that
be hopeful
but as we walked back along the lane
that evening towards stovey in the horse
in colors Holmes seemed somewhat less
certain I have little to go on at this
moment except Instinct Watson I do not
feel that Jack Carpenter killed Henry
weeks and I feel even more strongly that
that young woman did not do it either
but feelings I'm afraid are not evidence
let's hurry back to the end and hope the
bar is still available to us then we can
make an assessment of these matters in
Comfort
the Inn was closed customers when we
arrived but Mr Carpenter hastily
provided us with a bottle of whiskey and
some bread and cheese
the fire was still glowing bright and I
sat there for a good hour while my
friend went away to ask some questions
of our host
eventually he returned and reclaimed his
seat beside the fire
can we number the suspects in this case
Watson well apart from Jack Carpenter
and the girl Beth Miller I said dropping
my voice
I suppose Jack's father our landlord is
another possibility
yes and since we know he saw jack off
onto the train either he or his son
would have needed to commit the murder
sometime earlier but how early
I've just spoken to him at length he
assures me and I believe him that there
are plenty of people prepared to swear
that both he and Jack were here all
afternoon and Beth spent the day at farm
work
even so
if the police go ahead and prosecute a
case against one or all of them there's
a strong chance a jury might find them
guilty based purely on the assumption
that they would at some time have had
the opportunity
we are not out of the woods yet Watson I
see what you mean our inquiries seem to
have stalled rather
I refilled our glasses from the whiskey
bottle and Holmes puffed at his pipe
then suddenly he said the secret is on
that train Watson I'm sure that's where
it is what time is it 20 minutes to 11.
come along we might just get there
before it leaves
it was an old cut that transported US
post heaths along the hold and muddy
Lanes of stovey so that we arrived at
the station splattered and not a little
shaken we were however in good time to
meet the 1059 unfortunately for us the
station Master Mr Milton Fraser was
again on duty despite his obvious
respect for my friend however he became
instantly resistant on hearing Holmes's
request
no sir I'm afraid I most definitely
cannot hold up the 1059 London train
Mr Fraser this is no flippant request an
innocent young woman will spend tonight
locked in a dungeon as will her fiance
unless I am able to complete certain
essential inquiries I ask only for 10
minutes
Mr romes my reputation may be a small
thing by the world's standards but it is
very important to me 10 minutes is a
long time to delay a train
but if I can guarantee you that this
will not affect your reputation can you
really do that sir
Mr Fraser you have my word on it
a long thoughtful pause then
very well Mr Holmes
I'll do as you ask
when two minutes later the great black
locomotive hauled its clanking carriages
into the station Mr Milton Fraser went
straight to the footplate and had words
with the engineer
a wave to Holmes and myself who were
some way along the platform told us all
was clear and we boarded the train
Holmes went directly to the second
compartment of the third Carriage which
contained just one late passenger an
elderly gentleman sitting beside what I
saw immediately to be the medical bag of
a general practitioner
if I may interrupt your peace and quiet
sir home said and having outlined his
reasons asked were you aboard this train
last night
I was said the older man I take this
train pretty well every night I'm a
medical man with a practice in Newbury
and a home in London
were you in this same compartment last
night the elderly physician laughed
creature of habit sir same compartment
every night
and do you recollect the young man who I
believe got onto the train at this
station yesterday
do is a matter of fact he sat there
right opposite me by the window
Pleasant young man good now sir the
train stopped at dark Hill crossing a
little way up the line do you recall
anything unusual about that
oh it stops there pretty well every
night but well
I do remember something as a matter of
fact
the train whistled as it usually does to
see if the downtrain is close enough to
respond
at just that moment I remarked a small
flash of light outside the train like
the sun reflecting off brass and the
young man said Holmes
what was his response
he seemed as puzzled as I was
he said he knew the area and couldn't
imagine what it could be thank you
doctor said Holmes he led me briskly
from the Train
we have just three of our 10 minutes
left before the train leaves Watson but
I think it might just be enough
Mr Fraser was waiting for us on the
platform
all done sir
at one final request Mr Fraser are these
the same carriages and in the same order
as made up the train last night
yes sir that doesn't change much
then I'll need to get onto the line to
check the other side of the train I
don't know Mr ohms the downtrain is due
you'll be at too much risk I shall be
quick and without further discussion he
re-entered the train crossed the
compartment opened the further door and
dropped onto the downline Beyond at
almost precisely that moment we heard a
whistle and Fraser said by golly Dr
Watson that's the downtrend crossing the
bridge
I waited for a half minute but when I
heard the rumble of the approaching
train I could restrain myself no longer
Holmes I called get a move on for God's
sake but the last words of my sentence
were drowned by the Roar of a locomotive
thundering into the station and hissing
to a halt next to the 10 59.
I'm not sure what I thought had happened
I could see that Holmes had not regained
the empty compartment for a terrible
moment I hovered in a cloud of anxiety
then his head appeared between the
bottom of the train and the platform
Edge he had ducked under the stationary
train to avoid the incoming Express
Homes
are you all right more than all right
Watson he said as he clambered back onto
the platform
especially as I believe I can now name
our murderer he turned to the rather
shaken station master
the train may leave Mr Fraser but there
are conditions I see there are no
facilities for uncoupling a carriage
here in stovey
correct sir there are no sightings here
then I must ask you to travel to London
with the train and to ensure on arrival
that the carriage in which the physician
gentleman is traveling is impounded at
Paddington
good Lord Mr ohms is the doctor a
suspect
no Mr Fraser but one might say the
carriage is
despite his misgivings the station
master was heroically compliant and
directly he had arranged for a message
to be sent to his own family he boarded
the 1059 which had now for one night
only become the 11 25 and the train
pulled out of the station on its way to
London
well Holmes I probably don't need to
tell you I said that I am completely
baffled
you can be forgiven for that Watson
it has been a puzzling business but you
do intend to explain to me how a trained
Carriage can be a suspect in a murder
case I will explain everything when we
get back to the horse in colors but
first I must ensure that Beth Miller is
released from that appalling prison and
spends tonight in her own bed
it was long past midnight when we sat
again in the comfort of the Inn
though I had not been present when
Holmes had put his theory before
Sergeant Berry at the makeshift jail he
had clearly made a convincing argument
because Beth Miller had been immediately
released and sat with us now at the
rough hewn table where Samuel Carpenter
bubbling with the turn in Fortune was
proving very liberal with his best ale
so who was it Mr ohms who was the
murderer
well that's not a simpler question to
answer as you might think said Holmes
the simple answer is that Henry weeks
was the murderer
do you mean it was suicide I said well
Watson whatever we call it that is no
doubt that when Henry weeks fired the
gun it was to Murder Jack Carpenter
around the table Mr Carpenter Beth
Miller and I all wearing similar baffled
Expressions sets staring at homes
waiting for him to elucidate
Henry weeks home said went to the spot
with the intention of killing Young Jack
he knew the train would stop there and
he meant to get a shot at his victim
through the carriage window
things seem to be going well for him
Jack Carpenter was sitting on the stovey
side of the train so weeks would have
had a good view of him from the lane
here is what I believe happened weeks
took aim but at the very moment he was
about to squeeze the trigger the train
blew its whistle
my guess is that the horse reared up and
kicked the butt of the gun hence that
wound on the beast's foreleg the gun
went off ah said I that flash of light
the physician on the train mentioned
precisely the sound of the shot was
probably drowned by the noise of the
Train the gun battle now tilted down its
aim sent low the bullet hit the wheel
bogey of the carriage the mark on the
metalwork is what I was so Keen to check
this evening and ricocheted back to
strike Henry weeks
so the train wheel was the killer I said
as I say one could impute the train or
the bullet or even the horse as
accessories for all were material in the
death
but the fact of the matter is that Henry
weeks in a rather elegant example of
poetic justice inadvertently murdered
himself
Holmes and I took the first train back
to London the following morning passing
on our way out of stovey station the
site of weeks's lonely death
put you onto it homes I asked
I suppose you could say Watson that
human goodness put me onto it not
deduction then
Samuel Carpenter his son jack Beth
Miller good people Watson
we were if my instinct about them was
correct distinctly short of homicidal
candidates
then you'll recollect the nature of
weeks's head wound clearly not suicide
as you noted yourself because of the
shallow nature of the wound but was it a
deep enough lesion to have been caused
by a direct hit at close range
that set me wondering about whether the
bullet might have rebounded
my examination of the train confirmed it
you're quite right about the wound
I dare say it didn't kill him outright
the poor man probably lay there for some
while bleeding to death in the cold well
said Holmes perhaps that Bleak hour may
have given him time to reconsider the
error of his ways
foreign
homes the rediscovered Railway Mysteries
and Other Stories was written by John
Taylor and read by Benedict Cumberbatch
it was produced by fiction Factory and
is published by BBC audiobooks
[Music]
when I was young it contained the
treasures of Boyhood a catapult a lump
of beeswax the carapace of a crab
for many years since it has been the
repository of an archive admittedly Iraq